<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Business Musings | Lionhacks]]></title>
  <link href="http://guymorita.github.io//github/blog/categories/business-musings/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://guymorita.github.io//github/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-10T14:06:35-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://guymorita.github.io//github/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Guy Morita]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons from a young entrepreneur (Part 2 of 3)]]></title>
    <link href="http://guymorita.github.io//github/2012/03/lessons-from-a-young-entrepreneur-part-2-of-3/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://guymorita.github.io//github/2012/03/lessons-from-a-young-entrepreneur-part-2-of-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>

Continuation from <a href="http://www.lionhacks.com/2012/03/lessons-from-a-young-entrepreneur/">Part 1</a>
<h2>Management is an entirely different world than being a technician</h2>
</div>


<p>As I read in one of my favorite books, “The E-Myth Revisited” by Michael Gerber, we all have three personalities within ourselves – a technician, a manager, and an entrepreneur. The technician knows how to do the technical work of the business like baking pies, building websites, or tuning an engine. The manager knows how to monitor and organize the team/projects. The entrepreneur creates a vision and builds the business.</p>

<p>While the technical work is relatively straight forward, the managerial work is much more subjective and soft. Getting an employee to like you is relatively easy but getting an employee to consistently, happily carryout a project and never-endingly work towards the company’s benefit is an entirely different world. There is an infinite number of factors that go into being a good manager and no one is perfect. If I could list a few important factors it would be high integrity, timeliness, great communication, optimism, ability to make decisions despite ambiguity and a good listener. In my brief experience, I found that it was far more important for the team to respect me, than to like me. As long as I clearly communicated to them that my actions were in the best interest of the company and therefore in their job security. I’m pretty sure mastering the art and science of management will be a lifelong endeavor.</p>

<div>
<h2>Invest back into the company</h2>
</div>


<p>2010 was a relatively good year for the company financially. In fact the margins were so high that I thought the company was extremely successful. Higher margins are good right? Yes, however what I didn’t realize was that by keeping the margins high, I was taking away from how much better the service could have become. It was an opportunity cost to creating higher customer lifetime value.</p>

<p>With our margins at 30%+ we were creating cash flow; however we could have greatly increased the level of customer satisfaction if we had reinvested another 15%. Had I realized this before, I would’ve kept the margins at a safe enough level to survive and reinvested the rest back into the company instead of letting it sit in the company bank account. That said, when you&rsquo;re bootstrapping a company it will feel like you need to cling to every penny.</p>

<div>
<h2>Integrity is everything</h2>
</div>


<p>For the early part of my life this word has had a purely theoretical meaning. After receiving my black belt in Tae Kwon Do I remember it as one of the Five Tenets (codes of conduct), but even then it was just another check on the list.</p>

<p>Integrity is everything. Both in terms of self-trust and in terms of choosing team members who also operate with high integrity. Integrity on a personal level is being able to trust that you will carry out the things you say in your head. On the smallest level, it&rsquo;s going to bed on-time and getting up on time. If you can&rsquo;t actually carry out what you say you want to do, it will continually lower your self-trust. Can you will yourself to go to the gym 3 days a week? Can you quit smoking? Can you eat healthier? Can you trust yourself to do the things you say you will do? It&rsquo;s a very important question. It might also help to look at it from the perspective of the three brains, as I mentioned in <a href="http://www.lionhacks.com/2012/03/lessons-from-a-young-entrepreneur/">Part 1 about psychology</a>. Remember that if we were completely rational beings, we would go to bed at the ideal time, wake up at the ideal time, eat perfectly, go to the gym 3-4 days a week, work hard at work, cut everything off after work and be super happy all the time. Unfortunately, we aren&rsquo;t completely rational. We have 3 brains to deal with, not just one. And learning how and when your reptilian/emotional brains are working against you is important. The logical brain knows you should eat broccoli instead of potato chips because you will have better energy and it&rsquo;s extremely good for you, it&rsquo;s the reptilian/emotional brains that want the high that comes from the texture and taste of the chip. This relates to integrity just because you have to recognize when the reptilian/emotional brains are taking over and you&rsquo;re not being logical or operating with integrity.</p>

<p>Integrity is the core of business. Choose team members that have lots of integrity. This may seem soft or not applicable until you look at the opposite. Imagine a team where you couldn&rsquo;t trust anyone to do what they said, get it done on time or to the standards you wanted. How would your output be? Pretty terrible right? The ability to trust that you can carry out your own desires and the ability to trust the words of another is priceless. If you can’t fully trust your team to carry out what they promise on-time; missed deadlines, finger-pointing and a lot of uncomfortable conversations are sure to follow. This carries the exact same effect with dealings with clients.</p>

<div>
<h2>Get comfortable being uncomfortable</h2>
</div>


<p>As an entrepreneur I quickly found myself in tons of uncomfortable positions. Some examples might be the uncertainty of a new project/marketing campaign, an uncomfortable conversation with a team member, or new long-term lease to be signed. Calculate the risk of the project/campaign, have the uncomfortable conversation sooner than later, and talk to mentors/lawyers about the lease. Find as much information as you can about the situation, manage/mitigate the risks, and finally make a decision acknowledging that while you did as much research as you could, you have incomplete data. On a daily basis I had to make decisions based on 60% certainty. There is rarely a perfect answer. Nothing is certain, especially in business. Just like setting out to create a business, the most important part is the decision and action to start. Situations won’t solve themselves with time, especially if you’re CEO.</p>

<p>One of the biggest pieces of ambiguity I had to overcome was whether the company would succeed or fail. Rather than trying to convince myself it would succeed, I completely accepted that it was uncertain, dedicated myself to doing everything possible to help is succeed and accepted the results. Being afraid of failure and being attached to success brings nothing but unnecessary stress.</p>

<p>Many people that talk about starting companies but don&rsquo;t end up following through don&rsquo;t truly understand that often times in entrepreneurship starting is more important than planning. Take action now. If you have an idea, create an name for it Monday. Buy a domain on Tuesday. Research all the companies in the industry Wednesday through Friday. Take action now. Today. Not plan. If you think more planning is going to make the future more certain, it&rsquo;s just an illusion. Planning in entrepreneurship is often only useful as an exercise. The business model will likely change many many times over the development of the company. Build a solid team and vision, and like Columbus, set sail west.</p>

<div></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons from a young entrepreneur (Part 1 of 3)]]></title>
    <link href="http://guymorita.github.io//github/2012/03/lessons-from-a-young-entrepreneur/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://guymorita.github.io//github/2012/03/lessons-from-a-young-entrepreneur</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last 2 years of my professional life were almost completely devoted to building a company. The experience has been nothing short of surreal with swings up and down that resemble a roller coaster ride. The business which I started with less than $1,000 and no funding, grew to over $700,000 in revenue and created over 16 full-time jobs worldwide in 4 countries. Not the fastest growth that’s ever been seen, but certainly not the slowest.</p>

<p>Instead of thinking of the situation as a success or failure, I’ve treated the experience as a series of lessons. These lessons I’d like to share so that hopefully others can learn or refine these ideas and get value from them. All are from my personal experience and should be taken with a grain of salt.</p>

<p>Most of these lessons will have a business focus, but many of these principles are equally important in building strong relationships as they are in business. One small note is that many of these will sound very simple and they are. It’s not the knowing of them that I found important, it’s the internalization of the idea into something that you carryout unconsciously. And in my case, that only happened after I experienced it firsthand. I’ve cut it down to the twelve ideas I found most important but I could go on with dozens more:</p>

<div>
<h2>Create massive value</h2>
</div>


<p>This is the core idea that I’m still working on internalizing. The sole purpose of a business is to create value for its customers. The extent to which the company doesn’t create value is the extent to which the company shouldn’t even exist.</p>

<p>As a business owner, I was bombarded with sales/marketing problems, employee issues, office logistics, workflow problems, IT problems and everything else under the sun. On many occasions I lost sight of the fact that the only reason the company existed was to create an amazing customer experience. I valued the details of the contracts signed, the budget we were aiming to achieve, or even employee happiness over our own customer’s satisfaction. Delivering a great customer experience should be the staple behind every business decision and certainly behind the mission/vision. If you have a process that creates happy customers and a business model which makes money, so much the better. If you don&rsquo;t create happy customers and you make money, there are bound to be problems.</p>

<p>Another lesson from this is that if it comes between your customer’s happiness and your employee’s happiness, the former is more important. Ideally you can have both, but often times a decision has to be made which favors one over the other.</p>

<div>
<h2>Trust, but verify</h2>
</div>


<p>These are words from President Ronald Reagan. This lesson has been beat into my head more times than I can count. I experienced this with the sales director whom I had brought on to lead our sales team. When I initially brought him on, I was extremely happy with his performance. He created structure and processes that effectively drove the sales team. I trusted him to take the company’s best interest. I trusted too much and didn’t verify. Months into his employment cracks started to show. I saw contracts which were put together improperly; overpromising that had taken place and lastly, his attendance became sporadic as a result of his personal problem with crack cocaine.</p>

<p>Every entrepreneur should fully believe in his/her team’s abilities to carry out the vision; however, checks/balances need to be put in place to verify whether that trust is warranted. Empathize with what your team says, but see how their intentions match up to their actions.</p>

<div>
<h2>Psychology is important</h2>
</div>


<p>One of the most interesting things I’ve learned this year is about the brain. According to Truine Brain Theory, we actually have three brains, not just one. Each of which was developed on top of an older one. Our first is the reptilian brain responsible for basic life functions like voluntary motor function, eye movement, and other essential survival instincts. Next is the limbic brain (aka the emotional brain) responsible for motivation and emotion. And lastly, the neocortex (aka the logical/rational brain) which gives us the ability to confer language, create abstract thoughts, plan and perceive.</p>

<p>This is interesting for two reasons. First, the older brains always take priority over the newer ones. This means that your survival instincts found in your spinal column and reptilian brain, overpower the demands of your logic and emotion. So this is why if you see a car that’s about to hit you, your body automatically goes into survival mode, your senses heighten, and you unconsciously scramble for safety. Second and more interestingly is the fact that the emotional brain takes precedence over the logical brain. This is why we give into our compulsive shopping habits, burst out at a loved one and say things we don’t mean, or perform poorly when we knew exactly how to execute. For our logical mind to operate at peak performance, our emotional mind has to be positive and in a good state. If our emotions are out of whack, stressed, or negative, it literally makes us unable to think logically because our emotional brain takes precedence over our logical brain. Another way to put it is that “stress makes you stupid”.</p>

<p>When working as a CEO or as any role with a lot of accountability, remember that managing stress is just as important as anything else. For if your emotional brain becomes flooded with stress/negativity/anger, your rational brain freezes up and can’t make logical decisions.</p>

<p>This also has a lot of ties to work-life balance. Even though I was putting in 80+ hour weeks and sleeping in the office on occasion, I still forced myself to let go on Saturday and enjoy my personal life. I surely could not have made it as far as I did if I ignored my personal needs to relax and enjoy hanging out with my friends.</p>

<p>Though life can get extremely stressful at times, I think it&rsquo;s important to remember that almost all our stress is put in place from our modern social structure. If we take a brief look at Maslow&rsquo;s hierarchy, most people in the first world don&rsquo;t even have to worry about the bottom three layers. We don&rsquo;t have much to truly worry and stress about.</p>

<div>
<h2>Look out for yourself</h2>
</div>


<p>No one in the company is ever going to have the same perspective as the owner(s). Empathize with your team and understand their concerns; but realize that their motivations are likely much different than yours. Employees will never feel the full effect of all the liabilities, responsibilities, and accountabilities that the owners face. Realizing this helped me make many of the tough decisions when the team was in disagreement.</p>

<p>Solid leadership, equity incentives, aligned values and a clear vision can help to lessen the difference; however a small amount is likely to always be there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
